<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Farmadeus</title><link href="https://farmadeus.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://farmadeus.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://farmadeus.com/</id><updated>2020-05-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Farm Log 2020</title><link href="https://farmadeus.com/farm-log-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Ben Hanna</name></author><id>tag:farmadeus.com,2020-01-11:/farm-log-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;May 9, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started Winter Savory, Stinging Nettle, and Marigold seeds in trays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;May 8, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Divided the 4 Siberian Crabapple seedlings into separate containers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;May 7, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Received 10 Hybrid Willow tree cuttings in the mail today. Some were already rooting all along the stem. Placed 
in a jar …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;May 9, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started Winter Savory, Stinging Nettle, and Marigold seeds in trays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;May 8, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Divided the 4 Siberian Crabapple seedlings into separate containers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;May 7, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Received 10 Hybrid Willow tree cuttings in the mail today. Some were already rooting all along the stem. Placed 
in a jar of water to develop roots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;May 6, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The direct-seeded kale that we had appears to have mostly been killed by a frost last night. Tadorna Leeks appear to 
be okay. The lettuce in the coldframe is beginning to develop its first true leaves. Planted a Tolman Sweet Apple tree 
today that I ordered from Stark Bros. It went in place of the Methley Plum that was debarked. The Methley Plum had some 
sprouts below the soil line but I'm unsure if they're from the rootstock or the graft so I replanted it to see what we 
get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;May 5, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tadorna Leeks have adapted well and are surviving overnight freezing temperatures. Blauer Speck Kohlrabi and 
Superschmelz Kohlrabi are beginning to develop their first true leaves. Beets, carrots, kale, lettuce, and mustard greens 
have all sprouted now in the coldframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Reliance Grape cutting is showing signs of callusing so I've pulled it from the growing container and placed it 
in a jar of water to see if it'll develop roots now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started a tray with Cocozelle Zucchinni, Table Queen Acorn Squash, Tokyo Blue Squash, Nasturtiums, National Pickling 
Cucumber, Black Seeded Simpson Lettuce, and Big Boston Lettuce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checked on the seeds in the refrigerator. Many are starting to get mold on them. Pulled the Arctic Beauty Kiwi (&lt;em&gt;Actinidia kolomikta&lt;/em&gt;) 
into a small tray to see if they'll begin sprouting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;May 3, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built another leaf bin, this time down by our basement. Transplanted 3 Antonovka Apple seedlings into a 
large coffee can filled with compost, chicken manure, and charcoal. Direct seeded Blauer Speck Kohlrabi 
and Superschmelz Kohlrabi throughout the various garden beds. Left the tray of Skirret seedlings outside last 
night and some animal (a bird I think) pulled out a couple of the seedlings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;May 2, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transplanted the Skirret seedlings into cups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-05-02-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ECOS Pear seeds that were planted in the garden have started emerging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-05-02-01.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The various apple seeds are emerging also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-05-02-02.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green Beauty Peas are pushing up through the mulch. This will be the first year that I've grown peas with a 
heavy layer of mulch still on the bed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-05-02-03.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Constructed a leaf bin today. We'll let this set for probably a year, after which we should have some good leaf mold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-05-02-04.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;May 1, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a high of 74 degrees outside today. Got all the plants outside in direct sunlight with a light 
wind. Patches where we direct seeded kale and peas are all sprouting now. The transplanted Tadorna Leeks seem 
to be doing alright. Will plan on transplanting the rest this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asparagus spears are beginning to poke through in both the garden and the food forest. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-05-01-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 29, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moved 4 Skirret seedlings from the tray into cups to allow for continued root development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Methley Plum cuttings haven't been looking so good. They wilted and have many spots of fuzzy mold. 
Checked the bottoms of the cuttings and it doesn't appear that any have formed roots or even callused. The 
experiment is likely a complete failure. There's a couple things I'll try differently next time. First I believe my soil 
medium was likely too moist, which didn't really the encourage the cuttings to root and instead made them focus on leafing 
out too much. I also probably should've used some sort of bottom heat to encourage callusing. The next cuttings I try 
rooting will have the top ends sealed with wax to prevent drying out and then bottom ends will be packed in moist peat moss with 
bottom heat applied. Using the bag over the container just seems like it causes the cuttings to leaf out and grow mold more than 
anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Reliance Grape cutting is currently leafing out and has a little mold on one of the leaves. I've made some slits in the bag 
to reduce humidity a little bit. I also moved the cutting to the rear of the top of the refrigerator in an effort to try and give 
it more heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 28, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was a fairly sunny day today, managed to get all the plants outside again. Transplanted 3 Tadorna Leek 
seedlings into a bed. We are expecting some freezing temperatures next week so I'll be keeping them covered 
with a humidity dome for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 27, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it looks like I was wrong. The St. John's Wort that I planted never came up, it was the Skirret 
that came up. This actually makes me happy as I was really looking to getting Skirret started as a 
food crop this year. Below is a picture of what the Skirret seedlings look like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-27-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started 55 Siberan Peashrub seeds in a small tray.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 26, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did some pruning on cherry, pear, and apple trees today. Put a large cage around the Alderman Plum, if 
I don't the deer will make me pay dearly for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 25, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discovered a few parsnips from our failed crop last year that wintered over. Rather small but still delicious. 
Will see if we can get them all the way to seed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-25-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 24, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got most of the seedlings outdoors today. Tomatoes are getting big and starting to fall over. Been transplanting them 
into new containers as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-24-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunstan Chestnut seedlings are leafing out more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-24-01.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Red Russian Kale and Scarlet Kale seedlings have all emerged. Early White Vienna Kohlrabi is taking a while to sprout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-24-02.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harvested our first Egyptian Walking Onion of the season. This was from a plant that had divided into three. Cut off the bottom 
and replanted in another bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-24-03.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 21, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started a tray of Blauer Speck Kohlrabi, Superschmelz Kohlrabi, Tronchuda Kale, and Turkish Rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 20, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set trays of tomatoes, kale, and chestnut trees outside today to begin hardening off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 19, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the 50 Elephant Garlic corms that we planted in the fall, it looks like the first 
one has emerged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-20-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 15, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cold frame reached a high of 81 degrees today without being vented. We put a heavy duty tarp over the 
bed to prevent it from getting too cold at night. Maintained an overnight temperature of 32 degrees while outside 
temperature was 17 degrees. Weather is supposed to start warming up this weekend, so hopefully we'll see kale 
seedlings emerging sometime next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 14, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started a tray of Early White Vienna Kohlrabi, Red Russian Kale, and Scarlet Kale today. I'm 
making an aggressive effort to successfully grow Kohlrabi this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-14-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Methley Plum cuttings are now 4 weeks in and leafing out. In another 4 weeks we should be 
able to reduce the humidity and then check for root development. Hoping to get at least a 30% success rate 
on this propagation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-14-01.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally took the dome off the tray of Tomato, Lovage, and Tadorna Leek seedlings. The leaves of the tomatoes 
are a little windburned from being outside the other day but they'll recover in no time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-14-02.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checked on the temperature of the cold frame to see how it's doing. Was at about 50 degrees midday while the outside 
temperature was around 26 degrees. Overnight low so far is 27 degrees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-14-03.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 12, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discovered today that I may have accidentally cut the good cane off of my Reliance Grape when I 
was pruning the other week. The cutting was still green and not dried out so I snipped the ends, 
dipped it in rooting hormone and placed it in a container with a plastic bag over it. Hopefully, it 
may root and I'll get another grape vine out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-12-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 11, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a sunny, windy, but mostly warm day today. Leaves were dry enough that I was 
able to shred a couple piles to fill half of a bed that was still uncovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of the Glaskins Rhubarb seedlings I started last year are beginning to come up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-11-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Potato Onions have been staying strong with all the cold weather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-11-01.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Won't be long before we'll be harvesting some Egyptian Walking Onions. These are always 
my earliest onion in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-11-02.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making an effort to utilize every available space inside and outside of the fenced garden 
that I can. Finally put some logs to border the bed on the right hand side of this photo. We 
planted our excess Green Beauty Pea and Admiral Soup Pea seeds in this bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-11-03.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is our strongest Sea Kale seedling so far. I'm interested to see how well it does this 
year. I recently purchased more Sea Kale seeds on eBay from seller in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-11-04.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We took the opportunity to make a quick and dirty cold frame today. Used some old scrap lumber and patio 
windows that were left on the property from the previous owner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-11-05.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After assembling the frame, I flipped all the sod over with a garden spade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-11-06.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raked out any significant clumps and then amended with some shredded leaves and chicken run material. We 
wound up planting a mix of beets, carrots, kale, lettuce, and mustard greens in the bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-11-07.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 9, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weather has been flip-flopping back and forth between rain and snow during the past week. Managed to get 
outside yesterday and takes some pictures of how spring crops are progressing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another welcome surprise, I wasn't expecting Good King Henry to emerge this early in spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-09-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Victoria Rhubarb starting to push out more leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-09-01.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turkish Rocket is one of the crops I'm most anxious to try as it's a perennial member of the &lt;em&gt;Brassica&lt;/em&gt; family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-09-02.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reason I thought Caucasian Mountain Spinach would be a little more frost intolerant but this cold weather 
certainly isn't slowing it down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-09-03.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 5, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Direct seeded Dwarf Sugar Ann Pea, Admiral Soup Peas, Windsor Fava Beans, Red Russian Kale, and 
Half Gurnsey Parsnips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Located two more Sea Kale seedlings that survived the winter. Also started a planting box made from
some Quaking Aspen that I milled during the winter. Seeded Scarlet Kale, Siber Frill Kale, and Thousand-Headed 
Kale into the planting box. Placed the planting box in our makeshift coldframe, which is an old bathtub 
with a patio window I place over it at night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 4, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planted Green Beauty Peas today. Cherry trees are getting close to leafing out, the Juliet 
Cherries are the furthest along. I expect them to be the most vigorous growers in the food 
forest this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April 2, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I noticed today that it looks like all the Turkish Rocket seedlings from last year have already 
started coming up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-04-02-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've determined that Scarlet Kale is the most hardy variety of kale we've ever grown. The plants 
from last year are already beginning to send out side shoots. Unlike the Thousand-Headed Kale, the stalks 
of the Scarlet Kale survived the winter without hardly being scathed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The St. John's Wort has started sprouting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;March 31, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Victoria Rhubarb the I planted last year is already starting to emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-31-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;March 29, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replaced an old fence post that's about 4 - 5 years old. Lasted a good while considering 
it's aspen and I didn't protect the bottom part of the post. The new post is red oak. I wrapped 
black plastic around the base to keep the soil from making contact with wood at ground level. That's 
the area where rot usually occurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-29-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was able to locate the other 2 Caucasian Mountain Spinach seedlings. It looks like the Sea Kale seedlings 
from last year survived. I found one that a fairly decent root developed and moved it into the corner of my 
main asparagus bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dug out a large Comfrey plant from the bed where I usually grow peas. Broke the root apart and planted in various 
areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;March 28, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planted the 2 remaining Buartblack Walnut seedlings at the top of the hill. Moved a Chickasaw Plum 
seedling so that it'll be a shrub layer in front of the Buartblack Walnut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking down from the upper part of the hill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-28-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shredded leaves to place on top of the second potato bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-28-01.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Music Garlic has started poking through the mulch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-28-02.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;March 27, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spread manure on our second potato bed today. Also shredded a load of leaves and placed that on 
top of the manure layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last fall I originally transplanted 4 Buartblack Walnut seedlings at the bottom of our 
sloping hill. I believe I made a mistake in doing this, as it may create too much shade 
on the hill and prevent us from successfully growing crops there. With that in mind I moved 
2 of the seedlings up the hill to establish a canopy as far back as I can. The initial tree/shrub 
layer in front of the Buartblack Walnut will consist of Americana Dunbars Plum and Chickasaw Plum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two cages in the back of this photo are the Buartblack Walnut seedlings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-27-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last summer I planted out 3 Caucasian Mountain Spinach (&lt;em&gt;Hablitzia Tamnoides&lt;/em&gt;) seedlings. Two 
I haven't seen any sign from yet, but my strongest seedling is already re-emerging and sending out 
new shoots. It'll be nice to have a perennial spinach-like green without the fuss of starting 
seeds every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-27-01.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;March 25, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hauled the first load of manure out of the chicken run and laid on top of a bed 
where we will be growing potatoes and beans this year. I've never companion planted 
anything with potatoes but I've noticed that bush/pole beans work as a great companion 
for just about any plant. I routinely plant beans in between my tomatoes. This fixes nitrogen in the soil 
and the beans also serve as a living mulch, keeping the soil beneath cool and free of weeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My quick air prune bed design from the fall has experienced a failure. I didn't secure 
the hardware cloth on the bottom using wooden rails and thus the staples failed and the 
hardware cloth is now sagging. One bed I lost a good bit of bottom material from but both 
beds are still intact, they just likely won't have the intended air prune effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started raking leaves to use for mulch, winter onset so quickly last year that most of&lt;br&gt;
the leaves are still on the ground. We will shred the leaves using our wood chipper and then 
lay them on garden beds that aren't fully covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Music Garlic we have planted is beginning to poke through the mulch, also noticed a couple of our 
Rhubarb plants are getting ready to push out leaves. I checked on the Elephant Garlic corms we planted 
in the fall and so far I haven't seen any signs of rooting, though it did look like the hard shell on 
the corms have split.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Thousand-Headed Kale and Scarlet Kale appears to have overwintered well. Scarlet Kale stalks have mostly 
retained their color and firmness as they're the hardier variety. The stalks of the Thousand-Headed Kale are bleached white. 
I imagine for those most of the stalk is probably dead, though the plants should still send out new shoots from 
the base if that's the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;March 22, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started seeds today for Skirret and St. John's Wort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pulled seed potatoes out of the 5-gallon bucket root cellar. Potatoes are in good condition, 
don't see any that were compromised by mold or rot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-22-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-22-01.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;March 20, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started seeds today for Abe Lincoln Tomato, Black Krim Tomato, Black Vernissage Tomato, Chadwick's Cherry Tomato, 
Pink Bumblebee Tomato, Tadorna Leek, and Lovage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planted some Russian Tarragon seeds in a can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;March 16, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salvaged 12 cuttings from the Methley Plum and planted in a container to see if they'll root. 
Only about 5 - 6 are good hardwood cuttings so realistically I'm expecting to get maybe 2 or 3 successful plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-16-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cut the lower ends of the cuttings at a 45 degree angle to increase the surface area. The ends were then dipped 
in rooting hormone and placed into potting mix. Placed a ziplock bag over the cuttings to maintain a high humidity level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-16-01.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;March 15, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Placed Arctic Beauty Kiwi (&lt;em&gt;Actinidia kolomikta&lt;/em&gt;) seeds in the refrigerator for stratification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checked on the food forest and several trees were damaged by voles over the winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Methley Plum has been completely girdled. The best thing I can do is try and root as many cuttings 
as I can get off the tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-15-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Northern Prairie Apricot was completely debarked. This plant still has a good root system and 
has regrown vigorously after being cut down by deer a couple years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-15-01.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bartlett Pear, Superior Plum and the Toka Plum were also damaged but I believe these trees may be able 
to heal and survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;March 7, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Placed 27 Hybrid Siberian Crabapple (&lt;em&gt;Malus robusta&lt;/em&gt;) seeds in the refrigerator for 
stratification. Based on research this variety is a cross between Siberian Crabapple (&lt;em&gt;Malus baccata&lt;/em&gt;) 
and Plumleaf Crabapple (&lt;em&gt;Malus prunifolia&lt;/em&gt;). One source says the common name is Cherry Crabapple, that's 
what I'll likely refer to it as going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Progress on the can with Antonovka Apple and Siberian Crabapple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-07-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Progress on the can with Siberian Crabapple, there's five seedlings but one looks like it may not make it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-03-07-01.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;March 5, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue Hyssop seeds have started sprouting. Placed 30 Sargent Crabapple and 10 Spice Bush 
seeds in the refrigerator for stratification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;February 28, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planted around 10 Blue Hyssop seeds in a can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;February 24, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Placed 15 Winter Gold Crabapple seeds in the refrigerator for stratification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;February 23, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Placed Seaberry and Lingonberry seeds in the refrigerator for stratification. The first 
two Dunstan Chestnut seedlings are starting to leaf out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-02-23-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Siberian Crabapple seedlings have started sending out their first true leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-02-23-01.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;February 16, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Removed the remaining 5 Antonovka Apple and 6 Siberian Crabapple seeds from the refrigerator 
and planted in a can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;February 15, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Removed the remaining 9 Dunstan Chestnut seeds from the refrigerator and planted in 
cups.
&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-02-15-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Placed 10 American Persimmon and 29 Americana Dunbars Plum seeds in the refrigerator for 
stratification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;February 11, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siberian Crabapple seedlings have started emerging.
&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-02-11-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Removed five Antonovka Apple seeds from refrigerator and planted in a can. Placed 50 Hardy Kiwi, 25 Juneberry, 
and 25 Saskatoon seeds in the refrigerator for stratification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;February 8, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checked on the apple seeds in the refrigerator. Planted five Siberian Crabapple seeds that had sprouted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;January 26, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dunstan Chestnuts have begun to sprout in the refrigerator. One was compromised by mold. Pulled 
two out and planted in containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;January 11, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hens have started laying. Collected three medium light-brown eggs today. I'm guessing 
they're from the Golden Laced Wyandotte hens as I've read Welsummer eggs tend to be speckled.
&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2020-01-11-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Logs"></category></entry><entry><title>Farm Log 2019</title><link href="https://farmadeus.com/farm-log-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Ben Hanna</name></author><id>tag:farmadeus.com,2019-11-17:/farm-log-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;December 18, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at introducing a couple more plants in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burdock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;St. John's Wort&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stinging Nettle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recall seeing a large-leaved plant back in our forest at one point that I now believe 
may be Burdock. Will verify in the spring/summer if we already have …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;December 18, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at introducing a couple more plants in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burdock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;St. John's Wort&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stinging Nettle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recall seeing a large-leaved plant back in our forest at one point that I now believe 
may be Burdock. Will verify in the spring/summer if we already have this vegetable growing wild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;November 29, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Garlic cloves are a bit exposed, covered with a layer of leaves. Lightly pulled on a
couple cloves and they appear to be well rooted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;November 27, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at early spring bulb flowers for support around fruit trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Danford Iris&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Early Daffodil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Siberian Squill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Snowdrop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Winter Aconite&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strawberries appear to be a good groundcover for sunny edges of the food forest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;November 26, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at potential perennial herbs to introduce to the landscape in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blue Hyssop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lovage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roman Chamomile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Russian Tarragon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sweet Woodruff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Winter Savory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yarrow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;November 24, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planted Sargent Crabapple (upper right row), Various Apple (upper left row), ECOS Pear (lower row, right side), and Various Asian Pear (lower row, left side).
&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2019-11-24-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;November 23, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Air prune beds A (left) and B (right).
&lt;img src="/images/farm-log-2019-11-23-00.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;November 21, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capped air prune beds (A, B) with hardware mesh to prevent birds and rodents from stealing seeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;November 20, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planted 11 Shagbark Hickory seeds in air prune bed (A) that was planted with American Hazelnut on November 10, 2019. Covered with straw mulch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Removed Antonovka Apple and Siberian Crabapple from soaking and placed in refrigerator. Packed in moist paper towel due to small seed size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;November 19, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planted air prune bed (B) and covered with straw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Crop&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Seed Count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;American Plum&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ranetka Apple&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15 - 20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ECOS Pear&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10 - 15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Americana Dunbars Plum&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;November 17, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started soaking 10 Antonovka Apple seeds and 12 Siberian Crabapple seeds for stratification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;November 11, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stored 15 Dunstan Chestnuts seed in refrigerator. Packed in peat moss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;November 10, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scarified 20 American Hazelnuts with sandpaper and scored lightly with a knife. Planted in air prune bed (A) and covered with straw mulch. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;August 27, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Crop&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Yield&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Music Garlic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.5lb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yellow Potato Onions&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4lb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Potatoes (Reba, Red Nordland, Purple Viking)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9lb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;August 26, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cherry tomatoes have started ripening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;August 25, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planted Autumn Magic Aronia Berry (1) and Viking Aronia Berry (2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;svg viewBox="120 20 280 200" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"&gt;
    &lt;text x="180" y="50"&gt;4&lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;text x="200" y="60"&gt;1&lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;text x="300" y="200"&gt;2&lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;text x="320" y="190"&gt;3&lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;text x="250" y="120"&gt;5&lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;text x="310" y="110"&gt;6&lt;/text&gt;
&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;May 11, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planted Keewenaw Serviceberry (1), Wild Goose Plums (2), and Hughes Apple Crab (3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;May 9, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planted rhubarb.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Logs"></category></entry></feed>